<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A conference betwixt a papist and a Jew, or, A letter from a merchant in London, to his correspondent in Amsterdam</title>
            <author>Mayo, Richard, 1631?-1695.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1678</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 60 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50461</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1522</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10629</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13567971</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13567971</idno>
            <idno type="VID">100335</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A50461)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 100335)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 466:26)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A conference betwixt a papist and a Jew, or, A letter from a merchant in London, to his correspondent in Amsterdam</title>
                  <author>Mayo, Richard, 1631?-1695.</author>
                  <author>N. H.</author>
                  <author>Jacob, John, 17th cent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 34 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by A. M. and R. R. for Tho. Parkhurst ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1678.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed: N. H.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Richard Mayo.  Cf. BM.</note>
                  <note>Also attributed to John Jacob.  Cf. Halkett &amp; Laing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:100335:1"/>
            <p>Imprimatur,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>G<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>IL. JANE.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Jan.</hi> 9. 77.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:100335:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Conference Betwixt a PAPIST AND A JEW: OR, A LETTER FROM A Merchant in <hi>LONDON,</hi> to His Correſpondent in <hi>AMSTERDAM.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>A. M.</hi> and <hi>R. R.</hi> for <hi>Tho. Parkhurſt,</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> and Three <hi>Crowns</hi> in <hi>Cheapſide</hi> near <hi>Mercers-Chappel,</hi> 1678.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="dialogue">
            <pb facs="tcp:100335:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:100335:2"/>
            <head>A Conference betwixt a <hi>PAPIST</hi> and a <hi>JEW:</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Kind Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Ours of the 22d of this inſtant <hi>December</hi> I received, I give you my hearty thanks for the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents. It may ſerve in part for a requital, to remit you an account of a late Conference betwixt a <hi>Papiſt</hi> and a <hi>Jew</hi> at my Houſe. The occaſion was this: On the 14th inſtant, being <hi>Friday,</hi> a <hi>Jeſuit</hi> (one Father <hi>S.</hi>) whom I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways found moſt friendly and ingenuous, came to my houſe about Noon to get a return for 200 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> in <hi>Paris.</hi> I readily complied with his requeſt, and deſired him withal, to ſtay and take a ſhort Dinner with me. Without much importunity he was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded: My Dinner was only a Diſh of Salt-fiſh, and a joint of Pork roaſted; and though we had but ordinary chear, yet down we ſate, and were very chearful. Before we had fully Din'd in came <hi>L.</hi> the <hi>Jew,</hi> to diſcourſe me about a Commodity that I had inquired after; I deſired him alſo to ſit down and bear us company. My Wife knowing the Man, and his manner, ſaid to him, Mr. <hi>L.</hi> I am ſorry that we have nothing here that you can eat. I am ſure ſaid ſhe (pointing to the Pork, the only Diſh remaining now upon the Table) you are for none of this. Father <hi>S.</hi> (obſerving what ſhe ſaid,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:100335:3"/>
and ſuppoſing <hi>L.</hi> to be a <hi>Roman-Catholick,</hi> and that his Abſtinence did ariſe from the ſame ſcrupu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſity with thoſe of that perſwaſion) began to ſcrape acquaintance with him, and ask'd him what Countryman he was, and how long he had lived in this City? I prevented the reply of <hi>L.</hi> and told Father <hi>S.</hi> that I judged he was miſtaken in my friend, that he was no <hi>Roman-Catholick,</hi> but a <hi>Jew;</hi> and refrained Pork not becauſe it was <hi>Friday,</hi> and ſo forbidden by the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> but becauſe it was Swines fleſh, and ſo he apprehended it to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden of God. And here it would have made you ſmile if you had ſtood by, and heard what a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roxiſm or ſharp debate there aroſe betwixt Father <hi>S.</hi> and my Wife about this queſtion, Whether he or the <hi>Jew</hi> had the greateſt ground for ſuch Abſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence; and to ſpeak without partiality ſhe put him hard to it. After the Table was cleared, Father <hi>S.</hi> deſired to have ſome more ſerious Diſcourſe with <hi>L.</hi> and told him, that he wondered how any man in his right ſenſes could perſiſt in <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Infidelity; adding withal, that he would undertake in an hours time to convince him, that the promiſed Meſſiah was come, and that <hi>Jeſus of Nazareth</hi> was he. <hi>L.</hi> anſwered that he was a Trader, and altogether un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit to manage a Controverſy of that moment, and therefore deſired to be excuſed from medling with it. Father <hi>S.</hi> replyed, that it was more than probable there were ſome of their Prieſts or <hi>Rabbies</hi> in this City, and that if he pleaſed, he would meet the ableſt of them, and argue this point in his hearing, and he hoped to his conviction and ſatisfaction. <hi>L.</hi> conſented, and promiſed, if a convenient time and place were appointed, to bring a friend with him
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:100335:3"/>
for this purpoſe. I interpoſed, and offered my Houſe for the place of their meeting, which they well approved of, and appointed that day Sevenday at three of the Clock in the Afternoon for the time. <hi>L.</hi> deſired that there might be no noiſe or notice given of this their intention, alledging that it might be of ill and dangerous conſequence to thoſe of their Religion, if it ſhould come to the ear of the Magiſtrate. Hereupon they agreed that there ſhould be no words of it, and that no perſons be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, my Wife and I ſhould be preſent, but them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and <hi>L</hi>'s friend. Upon this they parted, and all three came punctually at the time appointed. I carried them up into a Chamber which had a Cloſet in it, where I had placed one that was dextrous in Stenography, and drew the Table pretty near the Cloſet-door, that he might hear and write all that paſt. When they were ſate, I made it my requeſt, that an intimate friend of mine who was in the Houſe might be permitted to come up and be an auditor. This was Mr. <hi>B.</hi> whom I had habited like a Gentleman. They ſaid if he were a friend of mine, and did deſire it, they had nothing againſt it. Whereupon I brought him in, and ſet him a Chair at a little diſtance from the Table. After a ſhort ſilence, Father <hi>S.</hi> began and ſaid to <hi>L.</hi> I ſuppoſe this is your friend you ſpake of at our laſt meeting in this Houſe, and promiſed to bring with you this day. <hi>L.</hi> anſwered, yes, it was; upon which they gave each other a friendly bow or ſalute. Then they firſt conſidered what ſhould be the main Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion or Subject-matter of their Conference, and anon it was reſolved into this, <hi>Whether Jeſus of Nazareth was the Meſſiah?</hi> The next thing they
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:100335:4"/>
conſidered, was, Whether this Queſtion ſhould be argued Syllogiſtically, the one taking the part of an Opponent, the other of a Reſpondent; or Whether they ſhould alternately deliver their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions in a continued Diſcourſe without inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupting one another? <hi>L</hi>'s friend deſired the latter way, becauſe he was not acquainted, as he ſaid, with our way of arguing in the Schools. A Third thing they reſolved upon, was this, that the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference ſhould not laſt above Two hours, and that neither of them ſhould ſpeak above half an hour at once. Having agreed thoſe three Preliminaries, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>S.</hi> began, and after he had a little ſtated the Queſtion, ſhewing whom he meant by <hi>Jeſus of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zareth,</hi> and whom he meant by the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded thus. Though I might urge many argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to prove what I affirm, That <hi>Jeſus of Naza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth</hi> is the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> foretold by the Prophets; yet I ſhall inſiſt only upon one. And that is, the many Miracles that were wrought by himſelf, and by his followers in his Name, which were ſufficient to convince the World that he came from God, and that he was that Prophet whom our Fathers ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, and that God had promiſed. I fearing that my Scribe in the Cloſet could not well hear Father <hi>S.</hi> he ſpake ſo low, (and indeed afterwards I un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood I was not deceived) made bold to deſire him a little to lift up his voice, which he readily did, and withal followed his argument ſo cloſely, and preſt it ſo nervouſly, that I confeſs I was great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly confirm'd thereby, and concluded <hi>L.</hi> and his friend would become his Converts, and wondered with my ſelf what rejoynder could poſſibly be me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditated by either of them.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:100335:4"/>His Argument he thus form'd: He that teſtified of himſelf that he was the Meſſiah, and confirmed his Teſtimony by many infallible Miracles, which were wrought by himſelf and by his followers in his name, he muſt needs be the Meſſiah: But <hi>Jeſus of Nazareth</hi> teſtified thus of himſelf, and confirmed his Teſtimony by many infallible Miracles, which were wrought by himſelf and by his followers in his name; Therefore <hi>Jeſus of Nazareth</hi> muſt needs be the Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiah. The Propoſition, ſays he, I ſuppoſe no ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal man will deny, whatever his perſwaſion be in matters of Religion; eſpecially if he underſtand by Miracles, as I do, ſuch wonderful Works as are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the courſe of Nature, and above and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the reach of any meer Creature, and as are the product of an Almighty Power. It can't be imagined that God, who is the faithful and merciful Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the Univerſe, would alter the courſe of Nature, and ſet the ſeal of his Omnipotency to a lye, and ſuffer the greateſt inducement of belief to be made uſe of to draw the world into error and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition. Two things I take for granted, nor can they be rationally gain-ſaid. Firſt, That none but God, and ſuch as are aſſiſted by him, can work real Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles. Satan and ſuch as are acted and aided by him may work Wonders, ſuch as may breed admiration in the beholders; but to work Miracles properly and ſtrictly ſo called, is above the power of Satan, or any created Being. This is the prerogative of him alone, whoſe Power is infinite and unlimited. Secondly, That God never did, nor never will com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate this Power to any of working Miracles to confirm a falſhood. To believe or affirm any ſuch thing concerning God, doth border at leaſt upon
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:100335:5"/>
blaſphemy. 'Tis as if God ſhould lend the Devil his ſeal to ſign his Deluſions, and ſuffer it too to be done in his Name, how then ſhould he govern the world in righteouſneſs? and how deplorable and remedileſs were the condition of poor mortals, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they have no way left them to undeceive them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, but muſt run into irrecoverable ruin, and entitle God to their ſeduction and perdition?</p>
            <p>That Teſtimony then which hath the atteſtation of Miracles, is undoubtedly Divine. Hereby <hi>Moſes</hi> did prove his Miſſion from God. <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and the <hi>Egyptians</hi> did not except againſt the argument, only they thought, at leaſt for a ſeaſon, his Works and Wonders were not ſupernatural, and that their Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerers could vye with him in works of Wonder, which we read in <hi>Exodus;</hi> they attempted by In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chantments and Diabolical aſſiſtance, till at length they acknowledged a Divine and ſupernatural Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to work with <hi>Moſes,</hi> and ingenuouſly confeſt that it was the finger of God. And had <hi>Moſes</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed himſelf to be the Meſſiah, and continued to work ſuch Miracles to confirm it, the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> and others had been obliged to believe it. They muſt have concluded, that no man could do the Miracles that he did, except God were with him, and wrought in and by him; and that God would never work with a Deluder, and lend him his ſeal (as I ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) to ſign his Deluſions, and deceive the world in his Name. <hi>Moſes</hi> therefore never had that pretext, but told the people plainly of a Meſſiah to come, of a Prophet that God would raiſe up to them of their brethren that ſhould be like unto him, that ſhould come with Signs and Miracles as he had done, whom they ſhould hearken to and obey.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:100335:5"/>Accordingly when <hi>Jeſus</hi> our Saviour was made of a woman, and manifeſted in the fleſh, the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of time being come, the main argument he uſed to bring the world to believe in him was this of Signs and Miracles. Hence 'twas that he told his followers, That the Works he wrought did bear witneſs of him: and when the <hi>Jews</hi> that were round about him askt him how long he made them to doubt, and deſired him to tell them plainly if he were the Chriſt: he anſwered, That he had already told them, that the Works which he did in his Fathers Name, did teſtifie of him. <hi>Yea,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>if I do not the works of my Father, believe me not: but if I do, although you believe not me, yet believe the Works.</hi> And again he ſays, <hi>Believe that I am in the Father, and the Father in me, or elſe believe me for the very Works ſake.</hi> He tells them further, <hi>That if he had not done the Works amongſt them that none other man did, or could do, they had not ſinned in not believing in him.</hi> This alſo we find to be the great argument upon which ſo many believed; when they ſaw the Miracles that he he did, they ſaid, <hi>This is of a truth that Prophet that ſhould come into the world.</hi> They had been in doubt for a while whether <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt</hi> was not the Chriſt; but anon they conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that <hi>John</hi> wrought no Miracle, but all things that <hi>John</hi> ſpake of <hi>Jeſus</hi> were true; and beſides he had done many Miracles, and therefore many believed in him. Thus much for the demonſtration of the Major Propoſition.</p>
            <p>Now I come to the Aſſumption or Minor Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, which is, That <hi>Jeſus of Nazareth</hi> teſtified of himſelf that he was the Meſſiah, and confirmed his Teſtimony by many infallible Miracles which were
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:100335:6"/>
wrought by himſelf and by his followers in his name. That he teſtified thus of himſelf is not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied. He told the <hi>Jews, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nleſs you believe that I am he you ſhall die in your ſins.</hi> This was the main part of that good Confeſſion which he witneſſed before <hi>Pontius Pilate</hi> the <hi>Roman</hi> Governour, and it was the main quarrel your Anceſtors had againſt him; for though they expected about this time the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of the Meſſiah, and that for good reaſons, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>Daniel</hi>'s ſeventy weeks were run out, and the Scepter was departed from <hi>Judah,</hi> and a Law-giver from between his feet, and the like yet they would not hear that <hi>Jeſus of Nazareth</hi> ſhould be the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. Alas! he had not the port and preſence of a worldly Potentate, ſuch as they dreamt of: <hi>When they ſaw him, there was no form or comelineſs for which they ſhould deſire him. They hid their faces from him, and eſteemed him not,</hi> as was foretold by <hi>Iſaiah</hi> the Prophet.</p>
            <p>That therefore which remains to be proved, is, that he confirmed this his Teſtimony by many infallible Miracles, which were wrought by himſelf and by his followers in his name. Let me begin with the Miracles which he wrought himſelf, of which there was a very great number, and that of divers kinds; and theſe were not done in a corner, but in the face of the world, before multitudes, and that in the preſence of, if not upon the perſons of ſome of his greateſt enemies. His firſt Miracle after his ſhewing himſelf to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> was at a Marriage-feaſt in <hi>Cana</hi> of <hi>Galilee,</hi> where he turned Water, and a great quantity of it into Wine. After that he fed more than once a great multitude, even ſeveral thouſands with a few barley-loaves and ſmall fiſhes, which were
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:100335:6"/>
ſo miraculouſly multiplied, that after they had ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten and were filled, his followers gathered up more fragments than there was at firſt in whole meat. He healed all manner of Diſeaſes, whether the diſeaſed were preſent or abſent; and this he did, as likewiſe his other Miracles, with a words-ſpeaking. Some of thoſe wonderful Cures he did on the Sabbath-day, for which the Phariſees (his inveterate enemies) did find fault with him, though they could not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny the matter of fact. He made the Lame to walk, the Deaf to hear, the Dumb to ſpeak, the Blind to ſee, concerning which the chief Prieſts and Elders had not only the atteſtation of by-ſtanders, but the Confeſſion of the parties themſelves, whom they curiouſly interrogated about the thing done, and his manner of doing it. He cleanſed many Lepers, and caſt out many Devils, which his enemies beholding could not deny, but blaſphemed, and ſaid, that he did it by Diabolical aid, and that he caſt out Devils by <hi>Beelzebub</hi> the Prince of Devils. Some who were dead he reſtored to life again, particularly one that was carrying to his grave, and another that had lain ſome time in his grave, even till his friends ſaid that he ſtunk. And this he did in the ſight of many <hi>Jews,</hi> who thereupon believed in him, having ſeen the Miracle that he did; yea the chief Prieſts con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulted about making away <hi>Lazarus,</hi> the perſon ſo miraculouſly raiſed, becauſe that by reaſon of him many of the <hi>Jews</hi> went away, and believed on Jeſus.</p>
            <p>The time limited for my Diſcourſe would fail me, ſhould I but inſtance in the twentieth part of thoſe many uncontrouled Miracles which <hi>Jeſus</hi> wrought in the ſpace of three years or thereabout.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:100335:7"/>
And when his hour was come in which he ſhould be cut off, though <hi>not for his own ſins,</hi> (as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Daniel</hi> had foretold) and ſhould <hi>make reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation for iniquity, and bring in an everlaſting righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs;</hi> even when he hung upon the Croſs, and was made ſin and a curſe for us, then there was a quaking of the Earth, a rending of the Rocks; yea the vail of the Temple was rent from the top to the bottom, and for the ſpace of three hours the Sun was darkned without any Eclipſe; which was noted as a prodigious thing by the learned Aſtrono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers of thoſe times, one of which is reported to have ſaid, That <hi>either the God of Nature ſuffered, or the frame of the World ſhall ſuddenly be diſſolved.</hi> Yea the Centurion and his Soldiers that attended, had ſuch conſternation at the things that hapned, that they feared greatly, and ſaid, <hi>Truly this was the Son of God.</hi> But above all, his Riſing again from the dead is moſt remarkable; therein <hi>he declared himſelf to be the Son of God with power.</hi> This fell out on the third day as he himſelf had foretold: And if this one thing be cleared up, it is inſtead of a thouſand Demonſtrations. Now the greateſt evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence that we can poſſibly have of a thing of this nature, is the teſtimony or atteſtation of others. This then is atteſted by a cloud of Witneſſes; they were not a few, but many, to whom he ſhewed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf alive, and that many times after his Paſſion, by many infallible proofs, <hi>being ſeen of them forty days, and ſpeaking of the things pertaining to the Kingdom of God.</hi> There are but two things that can poſſibly be objected againſt their Teſtimony. The firſt is, That thoſe perſons, who were witneſſes of his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, (as they called themſelves) might poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:100335:7"/>
be deceived, and that they ſaw a fantaſtical in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of a true Body. But this could not be, for they did not only ſee, but feel and handle him; yea, one of them put his finger into the holes in his hands and feet, and his hand into his ſide, ſuch was his incredulity. They did not only feel and handle him, but they did alſo eat and drink with him after he Roſe from the dead. If an Argument drawn from all thoſe ſenſes will not hold, how then can we be ſure that we our ſelves, and all the perſons we converſe with, are not Phan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſmes and meer Apparitions? And how could the <hi>Jews</hi> be ſure that it was <hi>Jeſus</hi> whom they crucified, and ſecured in the Sepulchre? In the ſame way that they were ſure of the one, his followers were ſure of the other. But if they were not deceived, yet, ſecondly, they might be deceivers. They might ſteal away the Body of <hi>Jeſus</hi> by night, and give it out that he was riſen from the dead next morning. Two things ſhew the incrediblity of ſuch a thing. 1. It is not credible his followers could do it. The chief Prieſts were aware that he had ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken before-hand of his Riſing the third day, and they foreſaw that if this happened, the laſt error (as they counted it) would be worſe than the firſt. Therefore they obtained leave of <hi>Pilate</hi> to make all ſure, and ſome of them went themſelves to ſee it done, and then they placed a ſtrong and diligent Watch to keep the Sepulchre. But here it may be objected, that the Watchmen fell aſleep, and then his Diſciples came and ſtole him away. This indeed you <hi>Jews</hi> believe to this day, and we know your Anceſtors hired the Watchmen to ſpread a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad this report. But then, Why were not they
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:100335:8"/>
puniſhed for their careleſneſs and oſcitancy? And if they were aſleep, How could they tell what the Diſciples did? And if they were awake, Why did they not oppoſe them that did it? The keepers for all their hire did make another relation of what happened; How an Angel deſcended with great ſplendor, whoſe countenance was like lightning, and roll'd away the ſtone at the mouth of the Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chre, which did ſo terrify them, as that they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came as dead men. Is it credible that the Diſciples, if they ſtole away the Body of their Maſter, would ſtay to ſtrip him, and lay the Linnen-cloths ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cently by themſelves? Would they not rather have carried him away in his Winding-ſheet, eſpecially when he was wound up in Linnen with a mixture of Myrrh and Aloes, which hath a clammy and glu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinous property? Would they not have been afraid leſt any of the Keepers ſhould awake, but ſtay and do ſo needleſs and difficult a work? But then, Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, as they could not do this if they would, ſo 'tis not credible that they would have done this if they could. Their writings, their converſations, ſhew them to be perſons of great integrity and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs; whereas if they had done this thing, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed upon the World in this kind, they would have been a company, not only of very wicked perſons, but of incarnate Devils. <hi>Mahomet</hi>'s villany would not have compar'd with it. What, to bely God in ſuch a manner, and to cry up Faith in <hi>Jeſus</hi> as riſen again from the dead, when he is ſtill under the power of Death, and no otherwiſe riſen than as they ſtole him out of the Grave! This would have been helliſh unparalel'd wickedneſs, and to be abhor'd by all men of common honeſty.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:100335:8"/>
But to put this out of queſtion, there were other witneſſes of his Reſurrection beſides his immediate Diſciples. He was ſeen in <hi>Galilae</hi> of above 500 perſons at once; many of whom lived a long while after to witneſs what they had ſeen: And had his Diſciples and others conſpired together ſo fouly to bely God and their own Conſciences, we may ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine it muſt have been for ſome advantage to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; but contrarywiſe, they knew that to profeſs Chriſt and the Chriſtian Religion, was to bring up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on themſelves and theirs the greateſt <hi>odium</hi> and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution.</p>
            <p>Yea God himſelf would have abhor'd ſuch Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creants; but on the contrary we find they are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved of God, and that by many miraculous ſigns and wonders which he did by them, and by that abundant meaſure of his Spirit which he poured out in extraordinary gifts and graces upon them. And this would have led me to the laſt term in my aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, that <hi>Jeſus</hi> his teſtimony of himſelf was confirm'd not only by his own Miracles, but alſo by the Miracles that his followers did in his name. For the truth is, they did as great Miracles in the Name of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> as ever he did in his own perſon. They cured all manner of infirmities, and that not leiſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the application of Medicines; but ſuddenly and miraculouſly by a words ſpeaking. The very ſhadow of <hi>Peter,</hi> one of his Diſciples, heal'd the ſick as they lay in Beds or Couches in the Streets. A certain man aged 40 years and upward, that had been lame from his mothers womb, was carried and laid dayly at the Gate of the Temple, which was call'd <hi>Beautiful,</hi> to ask alms of them that entred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Temple. To him this <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid, <hi>Silver and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:100335:9"/>
gold I have none, but ſuch as I have, I give thee: in the name of Jeſus Chriſt of Nazareth, riſe up and walk: And he took him by the right hand, and lift him up, and immediately his feet and ancles received ſtrength, and he entred into the Temple, walking and leaping, and praiſing God.</hi> This was manifeſt to all them that dwelt in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and acknowledged to be a notable Miracle by the Rulers of the people and the Elders of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> One <hi>Dorcas</hi> that was dead, he reſtored to life with a words ſpeaking, which was known to all the inhabitants of <hi>Joppa,</hi> which occaſion'd the converſion of that Town to the Chriſtian Religion. I might inſtance in the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles that were wrought by other Diſciples and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers of <hi>Jeſus.</hi> Let me conclude with a word or two concerning <hi>Paul,</hi> who was once mad againſt the Chriſtians, and did zealouſly perſecute them in every City. He was miraculouſly converted by <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi>'s appearing to him in the way as he went about this work to <hi>Damaſcus;</hi> a great light ſhone round about him, which his Companions ſaw as well as himſelf, and a voice ſpake to him ſaying, <hi>Saul, Saul, why perſecuteſt thou me? It is hard for thee to kick againſt the pricks.</hi> He was ſtruck blind for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny days: But anon the eyes of his body and mind both being enlightened, he preacheth that Faith which before he perſecuted; and, which is to our purpoſe, many ſignal and ſpecial Miracles were done by his hands, ſo that from his Body were brought to the Sick, Handkerchiefs, or Aprons, and the Diſeaſes departed from them, and the evil Spirits went out of them. But I forbear any further naming of theſe particulars; and having thus clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and fully prov'd the Premiſes, I hope you will
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:100335:9"/>
yield the Concluſion, which is, That <hi>Jeſus of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zareth is the Meſſiah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After a ſhort pauſe, <hi>L</hi>'s friend, the <hi>Rabbi,</hi> broke ſilence, and ſpake as followeth. <hi>Sir,</hi> I deſire you would have the like patience in hearing my anſwer, as I have had in hearing your argument. The Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion before us is of greateſt conſideration, both with us <hi>Jews,</hi> and you <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> and you may imagine that before now, I have debated it both with my ſelf and others. I remember ſome years ago in <hi>Portugal</hi> I was aſſaulted with this very Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of proving <hi>Jeſus of Nazareth to be the Meſſiah,</hi> by his working of Miracles; and finding that it was much urged by the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> I ſpent ſome time in ſtudying that point, and form'd an anſwer to this argument in writing, and that Writing I brought with me; which I the rather did, becauſe my friend told me, this was the Subject to be argued, and I did ſuppoſe you might happily attempt the proving of it by this very <hi>medium:</hi> And becauſe I have a bad memory, and ſpeak no good <hi>Engliſh,</hi> I ſhall beg leave to make uſe of my Papers. So having pull'd a little Manuſcript out of his Pocket, and turn'd over a few leaves, he made a fold at the place he ſought, and laid it by him a while, and thus pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded. As to that, <hi>Sir,</hi> which you call'd your Propoſition, I ſhall offer nothing in contradiction to it, it ſeems to be founded on the greateſt reaſon; nor will any of ours gainſay thoſe two poſitions you mention'd, 1ſt, That God only can work real Miracles. 2dly, That he will not, as I remember you well expreſt it, ſet his Seal to a lye. <hi>Jehovah</hi> is a God of Truth and Righteouſneſs.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:100335:10"/>But, Sir, as to that which you called your Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, it doth not in our opinion carry the like evidence and demonſtration with it. For to be plain with you, it doth not appear to us, That though <hi>Jeſus of Nazareth</hi> did teſtifie he was the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> he confirmed that Teſtimony by ſuch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible Miracles, either of his own or his follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers; nor hath any thing been urged by you for the manifeſting thereof, but what you have found in your own Books, which you cannot but know are queſtioned by us as to their Authority and Verity. And ſurely had our Fathers, and the Chief Prieſts of our Nation, ſeen any ſuch Miracles done by <hi>Jeſus of Nazareth,</hi> as your records do mention, they were men of that Religion and Learning, that they would not have ſo evilly intreated him, but would have paid him more reſpect and veneration. We believe therefore, as our Anceſtors have believed before us, that they were ſome of them Forgeries and feigned Miracles, and that others of them (pardon the word) were Diabolical atchievements. And we are the more confirmed in this belief, becauſe your latter Records and Chronicles do tell us of multitudes of Miracles, which were wrought as they ſay by men and women of your Religion, which ſeem to us to be very fabulous, yea ridiculous. Yet theſe are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived amongſt you likewiſe as certain and infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and have the approbation of your Church, and of the High Prieſt whom you call the <hi>Pope,</hi> and the Sanhedrim of Cardinals. And ſome of theſe do vye with the Miracles of <hi>Jeſus</hi> and his Diſciples, and ſeem to be much of the ſame ſort or kind. Let me name a few of many, and they are ſuch as I have taken out of great Authors, and licens'd or allow'd
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:100335:10"/>
Records. And pardon me if I don't cite the Author and places where they are chronicled; if you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire it I can produce my vouchers for every ſtory, and thoſe ſuch as are authentick. Then taking up his little book, and putting on a pair of Spectacles, he read as followeth. Your words, ſaid he, do firſt make mention of <hi>Jeſus</hi> his miraculous Conception, before they ſpeak of his and his followers miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous actions. This I have heard urged by others, though it was omitted by you, How he was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived of the Holy Spirit, and then born of a Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin without the knowledg of man. A like Miracle is recorded in one of your Church-hiſtories pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſht not long ſince with allowance; how St. <hi>Ken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigerne</hi>'s Mother begged of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> that ſhe might imitate his Virgin-mother in the conception and birth of a child: accordingly within a little time ſhe finds her ſelf with child, but often proteſts ſhe never knew any man. But by the Law of that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try where ſhe lived, ſhe muſt be caſt headlong from the top of a high mountain. She weeps and prays, but the Executioner does his work, down ſhe falls, but is ſo far from being kill'd or daſht in pieces, that ſhe has no bruiſe or hurt. Then ſhe is carried on ſhipboard many miles into the Sea, and there turned out into a ſmall boat of leather, deſtitute of all humane help; yet with great ſpeed and ſafety ſhe arriveth at a far diſtant Port; and landing, ſhe is delivered of that admirable Saint, and miraculouſly conceived ſon, St. <hi>Kentigerne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to Miraculous actions, the forementioned book, and others of equal or greater authority, will afford plenty that do not only compare with, but exceed the Miracles of <hi>Jeſus</hi> and his Diſciples. As for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanee,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:100335:11"/>
your Records ſpeak of Jeſus his faſting for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty days; and I can ſhew you where 'tis recorded of St. <hi>Patrick,</hi> that he faſted a whole Lent, (which I think with you is forty days) without any humane ſuſtenance, where one St. <hi>Ardan</hi> is ſaid to faſt full fifty days, and to grow fatter upon it.</p>
            <p>And whereas it is ſaid, That Jeſus fed five thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand perſons with five loaves and two ſmall fiſhes, St. <hi>Patrick</hi> is ſaid to have fed fourteen thouſand men with one Cow, two Stags, and two wild Boars; and it was talkt how next day the Cow was alive again.</p>
            <p>And as for Jeſus his turning Water into Wine, it is not ſo much as is commonly affirmed of your Prieſts, how by repeating four or five words, they can turn Wine into Blood, and Bread into Fleſh, and that the Fleſh and Blood of Jeſus himſelf; though you affirm he is aſcended into Heaven, and ſhall there remain till his ſecond coming. And it is recorded of one <hi>Odo</hi> an Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> that when ſome of his Clergy did doubt of ſuch Tranſmutation or Tranſubſtantiation, that he pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with tears whilſt he was at Maſs, that God would convince them by a ſign; and the body of Jeſus which he held in his hands (that is the bread) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to pour forth blood into the Chalice; which they perceiving, deſired the Prelate to pray that the blood might be changed again, leſt vengeance ſhould fall upon them for their incredulity; he doth ſo, and it became wine.</p>
            <p>Again, whereas your Records ſpeak how Jeſus and his Diſciples did heal all manner of Diſeaſes, whether the Diſeaſed were preſent or abſent, and that with a words ſpeaking; the like is alſo recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:100335:11"/>
of ſome of his more modern followers. Take for inſtance St. <hi>David</hi> a great light of the Church, as he is called; He invited St. <hi>Kined</hi> to come to his Synod; St. <hi>Kined</hi> excuſed himſelf, becauſe he was lame and crooked, unfit for ſuch holy company, and unable for ſo great a journey: Whereupon St. <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> prays him ſtrait and ſound. But the other ſtill delayed his coming; upon which St. <hi>David</hi> unprays his former prayer, and he becomes lame and crooked again. St. <hi>Bernard</hi> had great ſucceſs, as appears in your Hiſtories this way, for he cured one in <hi>Spain</hi> of a fore diſeaſe whilſt he was in <hi>France;</hi> he cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red one of a Dropſie by putting his own girdle a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout him; another of the Head-ach by ſending him his cap to wear; another that lay a dying, he reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by ſending him his coat; with a many more of the like kind.</p>
            <p>As for caſting out of Devils, nothing is more or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary than for your Prieſts to do that feat by their Exorciſms; your holy water with the ſign of the Croſs is ſaid to be frequently ſucceſsful in this work. And I find in one of your Hiſtories, how a Woman was diſpoſſeſt of ſeven Devils at <hi>Lauretto</hi> by calling on the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> for help; and when four were caſt out, the other three called <hi>Heroth, Horribilis,</hi> and <hi>Arcto,</hi> with much difficulty were removed, one crys out, <hi>Mary, Mary, thou art too cruel againſt us;</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other howled lamentably, and ſaid, <hi>Mary, thou art too powerful in this place, where thou doſt force us out of our poſſeſſion againſt our will.</hi> And the Prieſt, who by <hi>Mary</hi>'s aid did this Miracle, made him tell what place that was: who anſwered, it was the Virgins Bed-chamber, wherein after the Angel <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briel</hi>'s meſſage, ſhe conceived God; which was, as
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:100335:12"/>
other Hiſtories ſpeak, brought thither by a Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle. Nay, ſome of your great Saints have contend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the Devil and worſted him; as St. <hi>Dunſtan,</hi> who catch'd him by the Noſe with a pair of hot Tongs, and plucked him ſo hard, that the Devil was glad to ſhift from him by breaking down a Wall, crying out, it did ſo ſmart, once and again, oh what hath this Bald-pate done!</p>
            <p>As for raiſing the dead, this alſo hath been fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently practiſed. St. <hi>Francis</hi> makes one dye that anſwered his diſciples roughly when they would have borrowed his Cart, and afterwards raiſed him up again, and reſtored him to life. A man and his Son going a Pilgrimage to St. <hi>James</hi> at <hi>Compoſtella,</hi> light upon a wicked Hoſt, that firſt makes them drunk, and then puts two Silver Cups into their Wallets. They are purſued, and being taken and tryed, the Son was hang'd, the Father goes on his Pilgrimage, and returneth Thirty ſix days after to the-body of his Son ſtill hanging; he maketh grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous lamentations, till by and by the hanged Son began to comfort him, ſaying, Moſt dear Father, weep not, but rejoyce, for I was never better in all my life; St. <hi>James</hi> ſupports and comforts me with heavenly ſweetneſs: The Father overjoyed, makes known the buſineſs, the people flock together, the man is taken down, and the Hoſt hanged up in his room.</p>
            <p>I could ſhew you where St. <hi>David</hi> is ſaid to have raiſed a Boy from the dead, who afterwards waited upon him. St. <hi>Patrick</hi> to have raiſed one from the dead that was almoſt devour'd by Hogs. And St. <hi>Alban</hi> being to be Martyr'd, people thronged to ſee his Martyrdom, and crouding very hard by a deep
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:100335:12"/>
River, many fell in and were drown'd: The Saint perceiving it, prays that all might ſee his paſſion; and to that purpoſe the Waters may be dryed up: It was done accordingly, and thoſe that were drown'd before, are now found ſafe at the bottom of the River.</p>
            <p>Again, whereas it is recorded, that <hi>Jeſus</hi> raiſed himſelf from the dead: I can turn you to Records in great credit with you, where ſome of your emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Saints are reported to have done things little inferiour thereunto. St. <hi>Dennis</hi> the Patron of <hi>France,</hi> when his head was cut off, carried that head of his two Miles in his hands. St. <hi>Winifred</hi> vowing Virginity, was wooed by a Kings Son: To make her eſcape, ſhe pretends to dreſs her (for he found her much unready) and to return again; but out of a back-door ſhe goes, and makes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Church: on the ſide of a Hill ſhe is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertaken by her Suitor, whoſe love was turn'd into rage; and ſhe continuing in her obſtinacy, he cut off her head, and there roſe up a Well, which ſtill bears her name: The head tumbles down into the Church amongſt the People, St. <hi>Benno</hi> takes it up, ſeeks the murtherer, and finds him wiping his bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Sword upon the graſs; he pronounceth his Curſe againſt him, whereupon he falls down dead. St. <hi>Benno</hi> often kiſſing the Head, joyns it to the Body, covers it with his Mantle, and goes to the Altar to ſay Maſs; that done, to the Body he returns and begins a Sermon, and prays for the Virgin, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the People ſay <hi>Amen:</hi> Preſently the Virgin ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth up as if it were from ſleep, wipes her face from duſt and ſweat, and goes to the Church to give thanks: Only where the ſection was made, there
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:100335:13"/>
was a circle like a white Thred all her life. St. <hi>Clare,</hi> a Noble <hi>Engliſh</hi> man, to avoid Marrying a noble and beautiful Virgin, runs away to <hi>France;</hi> there a Lady falls in love with him; to ſcape her, he leaves the Monaſtry he was in; this turns her kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs into fury: ſhe ſends two Murtherers, who cut off his head; he riſeth ſtreight, and with his hands takes up his Head, carries it unto a Fountain, into which he caſt it; thence he takes it again, and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries it unto the Oratory of his Cell, and thence went forvvard to a little Village near the River <hi>Epta;</hi> where for ought appears he ended his proceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. My allotted time vvill not ſuffer me to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed, though I have collected ſome ſcores of theſe Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles; and indeed there is great plenty of them to be had. In one thing, to conclude, the Miracles of theſe modern Saints, exceed the Miracles of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> or his immediate follovvers; for they are record<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to have delivered Souls out of Hell-torments, vvhich <hi>Jeſus</hi> himſelf did never pretend to do. <hi>Gregory</hi> the Great (one of your Chief prieſts) vvept ſo long for <hi>Trajan</hi> the Emperour, that he ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained deliverance of his Soul from Hell, although vve read he vvas charged to ask no more ſo great a favour for any, at leaſt, that died unbaptized. So St. <hi>Dunſtan</hi> delivered King <hi>Edwins</hi> Soul from Infernal torments; and vvhen the Devils quarrel'd vvith him about it, he ſtopped their mouths by asking them vvhat reaſon they had to find fault vvith it, if <hi>Chriſt</hi> and he thought good to pardon him? St. <hi>Nicholas</hi> alſo delivered his ovvn Brothers Soul from Hell, though it coſt him Fifteen days and nights praying and weeping, as St. <hi>Antonine</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports. Now <hi>Sir,</hi> I think I am even vvith you in
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:100335:13"/>
point of Miracles, and muſt tell you, that we <hi>Jews</hi> (however we are charged with Infidelity) are not ſuch Infidels, or Ideots rather, to believe a reality in any of theſe Stories. Surely the Almighty Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er would not trifle thus with mortals. Theſe are therefore either errant Forgeries, or elſe devilliſh At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievements; and we cannot but think the ſame of the Miracles of Chriſt and his Diſciples, becauſe the one are recorded and received by you as well as the other: And therefore they are no proof that the Teſtimony of <hi>Jeſus</hi> was Divine, or that he is the <hi>Meſſiah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Father <hi>S.</hi> ſate all this while (as I could perceive) very uneaſily; and when the <hi>Rabbi</hi> had ended, he never looked up, nor made one word of reply; but his countenance as well as his ſilence, did ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue him full of confuſion and diſturbance in his mind. I looked upon Mr. <hi>B.</hi> and ſhook my head, I fear'd occaſion might be given theſe <hi>Jews</hi> to tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph if the Conference ended thus; and that they would be hardened themſelves, and would alſo harden others in their unbelief and prejudice againſt the Chriſtian Faith; wherefore I hoped that Mr. <hi>B.</hi> would take up the argument, and confute the <hi>Rabbi</hi>'s cavils: Nor was I diſappointed; for anon he roſe up, and drew nearer the Table, and ſaid, <hi>Sirs,</hi> you have greatly obliged me, in permitting me to be preſent hitherto in the capacity of a Hearer, and you will further oblige me, if you will permit me (now there has been ſo long a ſilence) to interpoſe a little as a Speaker. As my Diſcourſe is not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meditated, ſo it ſhall not be prolix. The Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment this worthy perſon hath urged to prove that <hi>Jeſus</hi> (our Lord and Saviour) is the Chriſt, is of
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:100335:14"/>
greater weight than to be ſo eaſily blown away: As you have already granted his Major, ſo I queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on not but you will alſo grant his Minor Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, when I ſhall make it manifeſt, that there is a vaſt difference or diſproportion betwixt the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Miracles that you have gleaned out of ſome latter Writings, and the real Miracles that were done by Jeſus our Lord, and his immediate fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers, as they are recorded in the Scripture. As for the former, falſhood and forgery is ingraven up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them in capital Letters.</p>
            <p>This will appear if you conſider how the report of theſe Miracles comes not forth till many years after they are done; or there is no mention of a competent number of credible perſons that were witneſſes of the doing of them. Beſides, the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt number of Chriſtians either never heard or ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver approved of any ſuch Miracles; yea there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing they have more diſowned both by word and writing, than the Legends of ſuch fabulous Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders; they have always accounted them as a ſubtle device of Satan the old Serpent to diſparage the Chriſtian Religion, and the wicked policy of a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Sect amongſt them to uphold an Antichriſtian faction. Let it not ſtumble you that I ſpeak of Sects and Factions amongſt us Chriſtians, they are found in all Religions, they are with you <hi>Jews,</hi> and they were of old with your Fathers, who were divided and crumbled into Sects and Parties, ſuch as the <hi>Phariſees, Sadduces, Eſſenes, Herodians,</hi> and the like. With us Chriſtians there is a great Sect or Facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thoſe who are commonly called <hi>Papiſts,</hi> or <hi>Roman</hi>-Catholicks, who have made the greateſt ſchiſm or rent that ever was in the Chriſtian Church,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:100335:14"/>
who anathematize and curſe all thoſe that are not of their Faction or Communion; and although they are numerous, and pretend to be the Catholick Church, and do fill <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>Portugal,</hi> and ſome other Countrys, with which it may be you have been moſt converſant; yet they are but few compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratively, that is in compariſon of other Chriſtians that are in the Weſtern and Eaſtern parts of the World, as the Proteſtants of ſeveral Kingdoms and Commonwealths, the <hi>Moſcovites,</hi> the <hi>Greeks,</hi> the <hi>Abaſſines,</hi> the <hi>Armenians,</hi> the <hi>Copties,</hi> the <hi>Circaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> the <hi>Mengreſſians,</hi> the <hi>Georgians,</hi> and the like. 'Tis then with this Popiſh Sect only that theſe ficti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Miracles are found; the generality of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans do openly declare that Miracles are long ſince ceaſed; nor was there any need of their continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance in the Church, the Chriſtian Faith being al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready not only ſufficiently, but abundantly confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by the Miracles, the infallible Miracles of our Saviour, and the Primitive Chriſtians, who ſhewed their Patent or Commiſſion under this Broad-Seal of Heaven, to the conviction and utter ſilencing of their moſt obſtinate enemies, both <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles.</hi> You know that <hi>Moſes</hi> confirmed the Law, and the Ordinances thereof, by Miracles firſt wrought in <hi>Egypt,</hi> and afterwards on Mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> and in the Wilderneſs; but when your Fathers were convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced of <hi>Moſes</hi> his Authority, and were once ſetled in the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> then thoſe Miracles ceaſed. So the Goſpel and the Ordinances thereof were at firſt confirmed by the uncontrouled Miracles of our Saviour and the Primitive Chriſtians, (as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed it was meet that thoſe who pretended a new Revelation from God, ſhould confirm it with a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:100335:15"/>
atteſtation) but ſince the Chriſtian Religion is now diffuſed both far and near, for the ſame reaſon all Miracles are at an end. As men water Orchards at the firſt planting of them; but when the Trees are well rooted, they do ſo no more. But amongſt the Schiſmatical Papiſts, Miracles are ſtill pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, who care not what wrong they do to the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion, or the common cauſe of Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, ſo they encreaſe their own Party. By means hereof, they delude the more ignorant and credu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous ſort of people, of whoſe ſouls their Prieſts make great merchandize. In King <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighths time, by the diligence of the Lord <hi>Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well,</hi> one of the chief Miniſters of State, many of the abominable cheats and forgeries of the Papiſts in this kind were made manifeſt throughout this Nation, which was one great cauſe of the Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that followed. And it is no ſlight evidence of the verity and Divine Authority of the Scriptures of the New Teſtament, that this was foretold therein ſome hundreds of years before it came to paſs; for ſo it is there recorded, that there ſhould be a great Defection or Apoſtaſie in the Chriſtian Church, which alſo ſhould be headed by the Biſhop of <hi>Rome;</hi> and though he be not named, yet any one with half an eye may perceive he is intended: never did Glove better fit a hand, nor ſhoo a foot, than the Character the Scripture gives of the Head of that Apoſtaſie doth agree to the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Pope: And con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning him it ſays expreſly, That his coming ſhould be after the working of Satan with power and ſigns, and lying wonders: In the Greek it is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, with wonders of a lye, an uſual <hi>Hebraiſm,</hi> as you underſtand, to note the notorious falſhood of his
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:100335:15"/>
wonders. And in another place it ſpeaks of a Beaſt (meaning the ſame perſon), whom the world ſhould wonder after, and worſhip too, and that for this Reaſon, Becauſe he doth great wonders in the ſight of men. This may fuffice for theſe lying Wonders, with their impudent Authors.</p>
            <p>But as for the Miracles of our Saviour, and his immediate followers, they are of another nature, and wear upon themſelves marks of infallibility; they are recorded in the age and places when and where they were wrought; they were done (as this worthy perſon well obſerved) not in a corner, but in the face of the world, before multitudes of wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, and thoſe perſons of known credit and inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity. Inſomuch, that your Anceſtors the Jews, that liv'd in thoſe days, and enquired diligently into theſe things, did never once deny the matter of fact, that ſuch Miracles were indeed done; but they ſaid they were done by Diabolical aſſiſtance? And others of them have ſaid, that Jeſus had found out the right pronunciation of that ineffable name, the <hi>nomen Tetragrammaton,</hi> and that it was ſewed in his thigh, and that by the power thereof he did all his Miracles. How ridiculous are ſuch evaſions: It ſeems evident enough, that many of the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees and <hi>Rabbies</hi> themſelves in thoſe days lay under this conviction, That Jeſus came from God, and was the Chriſt, and profeſt too their faith in him, though the moſt of them did it ſecretly for fear of the Jews; Who had agreed, that if any did confeſs that he was Chriſt, they ſhould be put out of the ſyna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue. <hi>Joſephus,</hi> a man of great Learning, who lived near thoſe times, and who was a Jew by Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Religion, in the 18 Book of his Antiquities,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:100335:16"/>
doth publiſh this paſſage to the world, <hi>That in the time of</hi> Tiberius Caeſar, <hi>there was one Jeſus, a wiſe man (if</hi> ſays he, <hi>it be lawful to call him a man); for he was the performer of divers miraculous works, and the inſtructor of thoſe who willingly entertained the truth. This was Chriſt, who being accuſed by the Princes of our Nation before Pilate, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards condemned to the Croſs, yet did not his fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers forbear to love him for the ignominy of his Death, for he appeared unto them the third day after, as the Divine Prophet had before teſtified of the ſame, and divers other wonderful things of him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let me deſire you to uſe your reaſon: Do but think with your ſelf, if the Miracles I am ſpeaking of, had been forged or feigned, how eaſie a matter had it been for the Jews, that lived in thoſe times, to have diſcovered and diſproved the fraud and falſhood thereof? Put the caſe there ſhould at this inſtant go abroad, a report of one in <hi>London,</hi> that did great Miracles, and that very frequently, that cured the blind, the lame, the deaf, the dumb, the diſeaſed of all ſorts that came or were brought to him, with a word ſpeaking; that he caſt out Devils, and raiſed the dead; and that his followers did the like, and that frequently in all parts of the Land; and that theſe things were done in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of thouſands, of throngs and multitudes of people. I pray you judg if it were not the eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt matter in the world to diſprove this, if it were falſe and feigned; and whether it were poſſible that whole Cities and Countreys ſhould believe it, and ſeal their belief thereof with their blood; nay, conſider whether the eaſineſs and certainty of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:100335:16"/>
this report, were not like to bring them all under the greateſt ſcorn and contempt imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, that ſhould publiſh it. You ſee the caſe is parallel, and I need not ſtay to apply it; 'tis ſtrange to obſerve, that the Jews of thoſe times, whoſe hearts were ready to burſt with envy and malice at the ſucceſs of the Goſpel, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver publickly objected the forging or feigning of thoſe Miracles by which it was confirmed. Yea, 'tis farther obſervable, that the Heathens themſelves, and the great ones amongſt them too, did openly aſſent to the reality thereof. We find it in true Records, how <hi>Tiberius</hi> himſelf upon a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter from <hi>Pilate</hi> concerning Jeſus, of the Miracles he wrought, and of the manner of his Death and Reſurrection, did move in the Senate of <hi>Rome,</hi> that he might be admitted amongſt their gods; and though they refuſed the motion, becauſe, as ſome ſay, it was not firſt moved by themſelves; or as others ſay, becauſe if they received him, they muſt renounce their other gods; yet the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour perſiſted in his opinion of Jeſus, and gave the Chriſtians great liberty all his days.</p>
            <p>Yea, the <hi>Turks</hi> acknowledg Jeſus our Saviour to be ſent of God, and that he confirmed his Miſſion by Miracles, and upbraid the Jews for not believing God by his Prophet Jeſus; and <hi>Mahomet</hi> threatneth judgment againſt them for it in his <hi>Alchoran,</hi> ſaying, that <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> was the Word and Power of God, ſent to convince the World by Miracles; That he was born of a Virgin, conceived without an earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Father by Divine inſpiration; that he cured all manner of Diſeaſes, and raiſed the dead to life a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain;
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:100335:17"/>
That he was taken at length into Heaven, and ſhall come again: Thus much of our Faith is confeſt by thoſe Infidels. I could go forward, but that I ſee the time is well nigh expired that you allowed for this Conference, and therefore I ſhall not be guilty of a farther abſurdity; but I beg your pardon for that I have already com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by an unrequeſted interpoſing in your ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious debate. And for a cloſe, I muſt tell you, <hi>Sir,</hi> that you muſt yield the Concluſion in this Gentlemens Argument, or elſe deny his <hi>major</hi> propoſition, which yet you ſay is founded upon the greateſt reaſon; or elſe you muſt fly to the evaſion of your Fathers, which is, That <hi>Jeſus</hi> our Lord did indeed work Miracles, but it was by the power of the Devil. And to ſay this, pardon the expreſſion, is no leſs than Blaſphemy: It is in effect, to ſay, That the Devil is God; and to aſcribe the Attributes and Prerogative of God unto him. For if Satan can do ſuch Miracles without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troul, to perſwade poor mortals to an entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of error, and to delude the World, who have no ſufficient means (as was ſaid before) to diſcover the deluſion, then it plainly follows that he is a God in Power, and the Almighty Governour of the World; or at leaſt, that God hath ſo little mercy, or juſtice, or care of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, as to give them to the power of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil to be remedileſly deluded by him: And he that will believe this rather than the Chriſtian Faith, deſerves to periſh in his blaſphemy and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidelity. I have done when I have made this one requeſt to you, That you will pleaſe to fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:100335:17"/>
me with ſuch another meeting, and I ſhall hope by the aſſiſtance of that Spirit which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds from the Father and the Son, which three are one God, the ſame in ſubſtance, equal in Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and Glory; I ſay by his aſſiſtance, and by other Arguments, and by thoſe taken from the writings of <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets, and ſome of your own <hi>Rabbinical</hi> Authors, clearly and convincingly to demonſtrate, That <hi>Jeſus</hi> is the <hi>Meſſiah;</hi> yea, the only begotten Son of God, and the Saviour of the World.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>L.</hi> the <hi>Jew</hi> was much affected (as I did perceive) with Mr. <hi>B</hi>'s cloſe and warm Diſcourſe (and indeed what with the matter, and his manner of delivering it, I think we were all af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected more or leſs); he turns to his friend, and deſires him by all means to accept of this Gentlemans motion, and appoint another meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Rabbi</hi> made a low bow to Mr. <hi>B.</hi> and ſaid, Sir, I heartily thank you for your plain and inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuous Diſcourſe, and I willingly acknowledg that I have received more information from it than from any perſon or Author that ever I yet converſed with; yea, what if I ſhould ſay, Within a little you have perſwaded me to be a Chriſtian. I muſt not conceal, that it hath been the opinion of ſome of our Learned men, That the Meſſias is come, and that for our ſins he lyes concealed. I have been often ſtaggered in my ſelf when I have thought of this matter. I dare not ſhut my eyes againſt clear light, but open them as wide as I can. Therefore, Sir, on this day fort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:100335:18"/>
at the ſame hour I ſhall gladly meet you, and, if it may be, I am content that this houſe in which we now are, ſhould be the place; only I beg leave to bring one or two of my Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren with me; and yet I deſire alſo that we may be private, and that not above the number of three or four at moſt be preſent beſides our ſelves. I told them my Houſe was at their ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and that I was rejoyced to ſee ſo good an effect of the paſt Conference; I called for a bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of Sack, they drank in a friendly manner to one another, ſo <hi>L.</hi> and his friend took their leave.</p>
            <p>When they were gone, Father <hi>S.</hi> applied him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to Mr. <hi>B.</hi> and thanked him for his ſeaſonable interpoſition, and deſired his farther acquaintance. I muſt, ſaid he, confeſs to you, That I am one of thoſe that you call <hi>Roman</hi>-Catholicks, but I was not aware that our Church by the Miracles ſhe approves of, and allows to be wrought in her, did give ſuch a ſtab to the Chriſtian Faith, as I now find it doth. I confeſs I have been long of opinion that thoſe Miracles of our Saints that are ſo much magnified amongſt us, are moſt of them falſe and fabulous. And I remember that I have read in <hi>Ludovicus Vives,</hi> a learned Writer of our own, how he calls the Golden Legend a Hiſtory unworthy of the Saints, and that the Author had a brazen face. Yea, he ſays expreſly, that the lives of the Saints are corrupted with abundance of lyes, and that the Authors did ſet down not what the Saints did, but what themſelves would have had them done.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:100335:18"/>Mr. <hi>B.</hi> underſtanding that Father <hi>S.</hi> was a <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi>-Catholick, deſired his pardon that he had ſpoke ſo keenly againſt the Church and Pope of <hi>Rome;</hi> adding, that he ſaw a neceſſity of it for the undeceiving of the <hi>Jew.</hi> And, Sir, ſaid he, give me leave to tell you, that your Church by her lying Wonders, and forged Miracles, hath greatly diſſerved and diſparaged the Faith of Chriſt, and gone about to invalidate the chiefeſt argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as you your ſelf acknowledged, for the confirmation of it. And let me add, that the <hi>Jews</hi> are farther prejudiced againſt Chriſtianity by the <hi>Papiſts</hi> amongſt whom they moſtly converſe, eſpecially in theſe Weſtern parts of the World, and that is by your Adoration of Images, the Hoſt, the Croſs, and the Relicks of the Saints; for they are great Zealots in the ſecond Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and utter enemies to all Idolatry. To which may be added, your debarring the general uſe of the New Teſtament, which is the probable means of the obtaining the knowledg of Chriſt, and the Chriſtian Religion.</p>
            <p>Father <hi>S.</hi> replied, that though he was a <hi>Roman</hi> Catholick, yet withal he was a Chriſtian; and I think, ſaid he, 'tis high time for me and all Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans beſides, to think of renouncing Communion with that Church whoſe principles and practiſes ſhall encourage men to continue <hi>Jews</hi> and Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels; and as the <hi>Jew</hi> ſaid, That within a little he was perſwaded to be a Chriſtian, ſo could he ſay, that within a little he was perſwaded to be a Proteſtant. Upon this they take leave of one
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:100335:19"/>
another, promiſing to meet again at the time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mentioned.</p>
            <p>Sir, I judged this Narrative would not be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acceptable to you. If any thing occurs in the next meeting that is worthy your notice, it ſhall be readily communicated by</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours in many Obligations, <hi>N. H.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
